[Music]
we've known about the possible
association between the consumption of
alcohol with excessive mortality from
cancer
for more than a hundred years
though the evidence is accumulating that
alcohol drinking is also associated with
pancreatic cancer prostate cancer and
melanoma
we're pretty certain that alcohol
increases risk of mouth cancer throat
cancer esophageal cancer colorectal
cancer liver cancer voice box cancer and
breast cancer
current estimates suggest that alcohol
causes about 5.8 percent of all cancer
deaths in these organs worldwide
here's how that breaks down for men and
women in men alcohol causes mostly head
and neck cancers and gastrointestinal
cancers whereas it's mostly breast
cancer in women
alcohol appears to cause more than a
hundred thousand cases of breast cancer
every year
yeah but is that just among heavy
drinkers
no all levels of evidence shows a risk
relationship between alcohol consumption
and the risk of breast cancer even at
low levels of consumption now eating a
healthy diet may help modulate that risk
yeah alcohol increases the risk of
breast cancer but a fiber-rich diet may
have the opposite effect and so eating
more whole plant foods may be able to
help ease the adverse effects of alcohol
alcohol has been shown to increase sex
hormone levels like estrogen which may
increase breast cancer risk
but you see the opposite happening
eating fiber-rich foods
fiber appears to bind estrogen and the
colon help flush it out of the body
but even so there does not appear to be
any level of alcohol consumption that is
completely safe from a cancer standpoint
so that's why you see commentaries like
this in the medical literature
exclamation point and all the
consumption of an addictive carcinogen
cannot be considered a healthy lifestyle
choice thus
the final message on alcohol should be
clear it is toxic carcinogenic birth
defect causing and potentially addictive
by arguing otherwise scientists can give
the alcohol lobbying advertisers the
opportunity to manipulate the scientific
evidence to place profits
over public health they do this through
denying the evidence
distorting
the evidence
and trying to distract the public's
attention
the alcohol industry big booze appears
to be engaged in the same kind of
extensive misrepresentation of the
evidence for which big tobacco is best
known
yet they're able to maintain this
illusion of righteousness alcohol
tobacco and junk food companies
increasingly seek to present themselves
as objective providers of health
information about their products
but health information should come from
health authorities not the 21st
century's most successful drug peddlers
alcohol industries profit hugely from
this disconnect though and sometimes
even appropriate the cause of cancer
prevention in order to promote their
carcinogenic product case in point
mike's hard pink lemonade joined the
fight drink pink carcinogens
associating the creation of their pink
ribbon alcohol with the death of one of
its employees from breast cancer
ironically contributing to risk in the
name
of prevention
who after all can forget
kentucky fried chicken's buckets for the
cure campaign
cancer risk is one of the things alcohol
industry won't tell you
but why doesn't your doctor tell you
there's relatively little public
awareness of the link and the medical
community has largely remained silent
the medical profession may be getting
more hip to corporate conflicts of
interest in general but why are we
ignoring the alcohol industry in other
words why is alcohol cancer's best kept
secret
maybe
it's because the doctors are drinkers
themselves and swan to remain in denial
over the whole thing
not only do most doctors drink a
significant proportion admit to drinking
while on call and report encountering
fellow physicians who are on call who
are apparently impaired even though most
doctors felt they had an obligation to
tell their patients should such a
situation arise guess how many actually
do
only 12 percent reported that they
informed their patients they've been
drinking
the industry has identified the alcohol
causes cancer messages a considerable
threat they have a vested interest in
maintaining the status quo of relative
ignorance uncertainty and denial among
the general population and their trusted
health advisors in the face of this it
is time the health professionals set
aside any leanings that might stem from
their own drinking and convey
unreservedly to their patients and the
communities they serve that alcohol
causes cancer
[Music]
foreign